YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series I. Departmant, Staff, and Committees
Sophia Smith Collection
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 06. Program: Series I. Departmant, Staff, and Committees
1870-2002
Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
Forms part of MS 324 UUID:b28ed807-7d99-4dc7-b852-0ec6db5aa000
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Records in this series document the work of national staff and committees responsible for development of the YWCA's overall program and general program materials. Materials include minutes, reports, publications, correspondence, conference files, studies, and training materials. Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program.
Historical Note
Organizational responsibility for development of the National Association program and program materials was especially fluid during the first twenty-five years of the YWCA of the USA. Initially, the Association divided its staff into a Home Department (concerned with work in the U.S.) and a Foreign Department (concerned with U.S. staff working abroad.) By 1909 the Association added a Department of Territorial Work to facilitate establishment of a single cohesive national organization out of the array of local, state, and regional organizations that made up the two predecessor organizations.
Though the National Association incorporated in 1907, the Home Department did not have its first meeting until November of 1909. This meeting brought together representatives of the Department's three committees--City, Student, and Association Extension-"to consider the questions of common importance." One of the first topics of discussion was a change of the Department's name to something that would better describe its responsibility for "developing and perfecting" YWCA methods. The group decided to change the its name to Department of Method at its second meeting in January 1910. Also in 1910 the Department of Territorial Work was re-christened the Department of Field Work and charged with responsibility for communication between the National Association and Community Associations on "standards, policies, finances, and work desired and contemplated." In theory, these two departments had quite separate responsibilities, but in practice, the staff seems to have been extraordinarily aware of the big picture needs of the Association and to have participated wherever and however they were needed. From its earliest staff configurations, the National Association seems to have remained unsure about whether or not it was desirable to divide responsibility for "method" and "services."
The Method Department's duties included making studies "to reveal the needs of young women in different localities and groupings," making "continuous study of the Association as a cooperative instrument of service in any community," and testing the "adaptability of its policies to different localities by a series of experiments conducted by expert secretaries." By 1913 those "expert secretaries" included specialists in city, and small town and country association work; in economics, education, physical education and hygiene, and religion; work in college and universities, Indian schools, secondary schools, church schools, "colored" schools; and work with "colored" women, girls, women in industry, and new immigrants. Method Department staff traveled the country visiting Associations and reporting on their area of expertise, but also on any other aspects of YWCA program they felt warranted comment.
The post-World War I staff reorganization and reduction placed specialist "subject" and "constituent group" staff in the newly-created Education and Research Division. The intent was for staff of the Division to act as a resource "to their colleagues at headquarters," but not to work so much with staff of local Associations. They were to carry out research; maintain the library and other resource files at headquarters (such as files on legislation and a clipping service); develop program materials and training courses on "girls as growing personalities," citizenship, general and vocational education, religious and social education, "constructive" health; and to correlate all material related to the educational work of the Association.
As the National Association's financial challenges continued, and the emphasis on national-level development of program decreased, the size of the program staff and its placement within the administrative structure changed every few years until 1960. It was sometimes part of the office responsible for services to Community Associations, sometimes explicitly part of Training, and sometimes a department of its own. Staff overseeing the National Association's public advocacy (which originally emerged from the Method Department) was often linked with program staff, but almost as often under the supervision of General Administration.
The establishment of the Bureau of Research and Program Resources in 1960 brought staff responsibility for research, program materials development, and public advocacy back together-though on a much-reduced scale. These activities remained linked, though under a succession of different names, through the end of the Twentieth century.
Administrative History
1907-09 Home Department
1909-19 Method Department
1919-23 Research and Method Department
1923-32 program staff decentralized in Field Division and Education and Research Division
1932-35 Program Dept of the Laboratory Division (incl also Pubs and Lib)
1936-39 Program and Research Department of the Laboratory Division
circa 1940- Program staff in Community Division; [called Subject staff 1941, Program Subjects staff 1942, Program staff 1943-44]
1945-circa 1948 Program Subject Department
1950 staff from former Program Subject Department listed under Training Services
1952 above staff listed under Leadership Services in the Membership Resources Department
1955 Leadership Services Department
1960 Bureau of Research, Studies, and Program Resources
1962-71 Bureau of Research and Program Resources
1972-circa75 Program Development and Public Policy Unit
circa 1975-c.1984 Program Unit
circa 1984-92 Program Services Division
1992- Advocacy and Research Division
Committees
1908-circa 1917 Secretaries [and Special Workers]: Minutes, 1908-17
1927-? Methods Council [program approval and evaluation]
1933-39 Review of Program and Budget
1939-42 Program Planning
Nov 1948-Mar 1970 Program and Budget Apportionment Committee
Oct 1970-Sep 1971 Program Coordinating/Coordination Core Group [interim group until Organizational Renewal Committee finished work]
Sep 1971-80? Program and Budget
Scope and Contents
Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records--Record Group 6. Program.
NOTE: For the most part, the Microfilmed Records and the Original Format Records do not duplicate each other and both should be consulted. This description covers materials in both formats. See the Contents List for a folder-level inventory of the Original Format Records. See the Microfilmed Records Reel Lists for a detailed inventory of the microfilm.
Records in this series include minutes, reports, publications, correspondence, conference files, studies, and training materials recording the work of the staff and committees overseeing development of the YWCA's overall program and general program materials.
As the home department for secretaries working on a variety of subjects and with a variety of groups, the minutes and reports (particularly those pre-1921), as well as the publications (particularly the Program Packets from the 1940s), provide an excellent overview of national program activities and the myriad of techniques used to implement them.
Publications and Resource Materials contain books, pamphlets, "work tools," forms, and kits covering techniques for planning program, for effective organization administration, a variety of political and economic subjects. They also include how-to guides on child care, running residences, space planning, and "world fellowship." The Program Series and Program Packets contain extensive suggestions for programs in all the YWCA's areas of concern. Because they cover so many different subjects, the various Program series and serials give an especially good sense of the scope of the Association's activities.
The series includes records of the Family Commission (1924-29), a group charged by Convention in 1922 to study the "character, place and significance of work in the life of women." The eventual study was expanded to include "work, marriage and divorce, and changing moral standards of today." There are also a couple of small files on other projects.
The bulk of the records date from the years of most intense National involvement in program activities, roughly 1906-39. As is true elsewhere in the records, few items have survived for the period between 1971 and 1988.
Microfilmed Records, 1884-1970 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
The Minutes and Reports are also available on paper.
Minutes and Reports
Program and Budget Committee
Research and Method Committee [includes Home Department and Method Department]
Research and Program Resources
Education Staff
Education and Research Division
Family Committee
Laboratory Division Committee
Leadership Services Division
Membership Resources Committee
Methods Council
Research and Investigation Committee
Subject Files
Economics
Education
Educational Work of the YWCA
Family Relations
Laboratory Division
Leadership Services
Membership Resources
National Board-Program
Research and Program Resources
YWCA--Program
Original Format Records, 1909-2000, n.d., 9 linear feet
[see Original Format Records folder list]
With the exception of some of the publications and the scrapbooks in the Miscellaneous section, most of the Original Format Records dated prior to 1971 are also on the microfilm.
The two (disassembled) scrapbooks were presumably compiled as a reference tool on structures and their uses for staff consulting with Community Associations. They contain information about YWCA buildings and buildings of similar organizations.
The original format records are arranged in nine subseries as follows:
General and History
Minutes
Conferences
Projects
Publications and Resource Materials
Reports
Studies
Training
Miscellaneous
Related Materials
All of the other Series in this Record Group contain information about different aspects of YWCA Program.
There is material about reorganization of YWCA work with constituent groups after World War II on the Microfilm under War Work, World War II, YWCA Constituency Groupings (reel 151).
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY, SERIES II. REORGANIZATIONS contains records of the various consultants' reports and studies of the administrative structure and goals that helped to determine the National Association's approach to Program.
Researchers should consult RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD for information about program in the predecessor organizations and discussions about program in the National Board and Executive Committee minutes.
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES contains records of the development of the National Association's overall program and the related discussions and ultimate endorsement of the program.
Information about Student Program was the responsibility of the Student Department and National Student Council and can be found in RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK.
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
A copy of the microfilmed records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records is available to borrow from the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College via Interlibrary Loan.
To request the microfilm from our library you will need to submit the following information to your library's Interlibrary Loan department:
Author: Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board
Title: Records, 1876-1970 [microform]
WorldCat Accession Number: OCLC 57415795
Notes: "Call # 689" and reel number(s) you want to borrow
Full descriptions and reel lists of the microfilm are available online.
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
Consumer education--United States--History--Sources
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM (overview)
SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES
SERIES II. TRAINING AND PERSONNEL
SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY
SERIES IV. CONSTITUENT GROUPS
SERIES V. PROGRAM SUBJECTS
SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS
SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
- SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Scope and Content note for more description.
  - General and History
    - Miscellaneous, 1929-2000, n.d. (Box 340, Folder 1)
    - Child Care
      - General and History, 1948-90 (Box 340, Folder 2)
      - "Women and Children First: A Century of YWCA Services to Young Children," 1984 (Box 340, Folder 3)
    - Home/Method/Research and Method Department: Policies and Program of the Department, 1909-15 (Box 340, Folder 4)
    - Education and Research Division
      - General, 1922-30 (Box 340, Folder 5)
      - International relations, 1928-29, n.d. (Box 340, Folder 6)
    - Laboratory Division
      - General, 1931-39 (Box 340, Folder 7)
      - Suggested Program of the Work of the National Board, Nov 1931-Dec 1932 (Box 340, Folder 8)
      - Proposed Program for the Biennium, 1934-36 (Box 340, Folder 9)
    - Proposed Program for the National Board, 1941-42 (Box 340, Folder 10)
    - Program Subject Department, 1946-47 (Box 340, Folder 11)
    - Decentralized Program, 1956-61 (Box 340, Folder 12)
    - Research and Program Resources, 1962-68, n.d. (Box 340, Folder 13)
    - Program Unit
      - General, 1979-84 (Box 340, Folder 14)
      - Chronological Correspondence, Mar-Dec 1983 (Box 340, Folder 15-21)
      - Resource Center on Women
        - 1969-73 (Box 340, Folder 22)
        - 1974-75, n.d. (Box 341, Folder 1-2)
    - Program Services Division
      - General, circa 1984-89 (Box 341, Folder 3)
      - Chronological Correspondence, Jan 1984 (Box 341, Folder 4)
      - Core Program concept, 1988-95, n.d. (Box 341, Folder 5-6)
  - Minutes
    - Department/Division/Bureau
      - Home/Method/Research and Method Department, 1909-10, 1912-21 (Box 341, Folder 7-14)
      - Education and Research Division, 1921-24, 1930-31 (Box 341, Folder 15-19)
      - Laboratory Division
        - 1932-39 (Box 342, Folder 1-2)
      - Laboratory Division Staff meetings, 1931-36, 1938-39 (Box 342, Folder 3-4)
      - Bureau of Research and Program Resources, 1963-70 (Box 342, Folder 5)
    - Committees
      - Ad-hoc Working Group on Strengthening the Family, 1955-57 (Box 342, Folder 6)
      - Counseling and Family Life Education, 1945-47 (Box 342, Folder 7)
      - Economic Sub-Committee/Committee, 1914-19 (Box 342, Folder 8)
      - Education Sub-Committee/Educational Staff, 1913-19 (Box 342, Folder 9)
      - Family Relationships: minutes and reports, 1937-39 (Box 342, Folder 10)
      - Homophobia Working Group, 1985 (Box 342, Folder 11)
      - Methods Council, 1927 (Box 342, Folder 12)
      - Program and Budget, Committee on Review of, 1933-39 (Box 342, Folder 13)
      - Program Planning Committee, 1939-42 (Box 342, Folder 14)
      - Program and Budget Apportionment Committee
        - Nov 1948-1952 (Box 342, Folder 15-19)
        - 1953-Mar 1963 (Box 343, Folder 1-11)
        - May 1963-1967 (Box 344, Folder 1-11)
        - 1968-Mar 1970 (Box 345, Folder 1-4)
      - Program Coordination Core Group, Oct 1970-Sep 1971 (Box 345, Folder 5)
      - Program and Budget Committee
        - Sep 1971-1979 (Box 345, Folder 6-12)
        - 1980 (Box 346, Folder 1)
      - Program Development Committee, 1983-86 (Box 346, Folder 2)
      - Research and Method Department Executive Committee, 1917-21 (Box 346, Folder 3-5)
      - Research Workers/ Research Bureau/Research Group, 1919-21 (Box 346, Folder 6-7)
      - Research and Education Workers/Research and Education Group, 1919-20 (Box 346, Folder 8-9)
  - Conferences
    - Women in the 1960s-Their Job World, a consultation sponsored by the National Board and the National Manpower Council, 1960 (Box 346, Folder 10)
    - National Conference for YWCA Program Staff, Nov-Dec 1960 (Box 346, Folder 11)
    - National Institute on Program, 1963 (Box 346, Folder 12)
    - National Staff Planning Conference, May 1973 (Box 346, Folder 13)
    - National Board and Staff Planning Conference, May 1974 (Box 346, Folder 14)
    - Opportunity, Equity and Change: National Conference for YWCA Program Staff, Nov 1979 (Box 346, Folder 15)
    - National Consultation for Programs on Domestic Violence, Dec 1980
      - General (Box 346, Folder 16)
      - Findings (Box 346, Folder 17)
      - Report (Box 346, Folder 18)
    - National Conference for YWCA Program Staff, 1983-84 (Box 346, Folder 19)
    - Consultation on Homeless Women and Children, Feb 1988 (Box 347, Folder 1)
  - Projects
    - Miscellaneous, 1963-74 (Box 347, Folder 2)
    - Family Commission
      - General and bibliography, 1924-25, n.d. (Box 347, Folder 3)
      - Summary of Work, 1926 (Box 347, Folder 4)
      - Minutes and reports
        - 1924-28 (Box 347, Folder 5-8)
      - Notes by Elizabeth Hendee, n.d. (Box 347, Folder 9)
      - "The Family in the Life of Today: Handbook for Leaders of Discussion Groups," circa 1926 (Box 347, Folder 10)
      - "Is the Family Essential to Christian Civilization?" Series IV, No. 9, 1926 (Box 347, Folder 11)
      - Preliminary Outline No. 2 To Discover What Women and Young Women are Thinking Today on Questions of Family Life, 1925 (Box 347, Folder 12)
      - Study questionnaire: Effect of Paid Work on Married Women and Their Families, 1929 (Box 347, Folder 13)
    - Women's Research Project (proposed), 1982-87 (Box 347, Folder 14)
  - Publications and Resource Materials
    - Abortion Laws: A Study Guide, Nov 1966 (Box 347, Folder 15)
    - Applying Educational Principles to the YWCA, 1930 (Box 347, Folder 16)
    - Child care, miscellaneous, 1950-72 (Box 347, Folder 17)
    - Clerical work, miscellaneous, 1928-29 (Box 347, Folder 18)
    - Consumer Problems and Projects, 1942 (Box 347, Folder 19)
    - Educational program in the YWCA, 1916, 1918 (Box 347, Folder 20)
    - Evaluating the Association Program, 1933 (Box 347, Folder 21)
    - Fresh Perspectives on Program Planning: A Work Tool for Testing by Community Division Staff Members, Sep 1960 (Box 347, Folder 22)
    - Fresh Perspectives on Program Planning: Guide for Studying the Role of a YWCA in its Local Community, 1963 (Box 348, Folder 1)
    - The Growth of Interest in International Relations in the YWCA, 1928 (Box 348, Folder 2)
    - A Guide to Program in the YWCA, 1963 (Box 348, Folder 3)
    - Guides for Planning Decentralized Units of Program in the YWCA, 1953 and Supplement, 1958 (Box 348, Folder 4)
    - Handbook of the Association Cafeteria, Blanche Geary, 1917 (Box 348, Folder 5)
    - Help the Illiterate Home Woman: A Guide to Developing Literacy Groups in a YWCA, 1967 (Box 348, Folder 6)
    - "How to be Effective in Politics: 'A Do-it-Yourself' Guide to Good Citizenship," 1963 (Box 348, Folder 6a)
    - In Summer, 1935 (Box 348, Folder 7)
    - International Catch-All: Suggestions for the study and practice of world citizenship, 1931 (Box 348, Folder 8)
    - International Threads Weaving Through YWCA Experience, 1929 (Box 348, Folder 9)
    - The Job of the Program Director by Dorothy I. Height, 1951 (Box 348, Folder 10)
    - Neighbors and Neighborhoods: A Housing Handbook, 1965 (Box 348, Folder 11)
    - "Open Letter No. II: "Is Charm Possible for You?," Dec 1926 (Box 348, Folder 12)
    - PACT: Peer Education in Sexuality and Health. YWCA of the USA Program Manual Series, 1989 (Box 348, Folder 13)
    - Patriotism-What is it?: Suggestions for Discussions and Projects, Assembly Programs for Washington's or Lincoln's Birthday or Other Patriotic Occasions by Margaret Hiller and A Vesper Service "The American Dream" by Abbie Graham, 1938, 1942 (Box 348, Folder 14)
    - Peaks of History: A Study and Discussion Course by Katherine Gerwick, 1922 (Box 348, Folder 15)
    - Potters and Pipers by Oolooah Burner, 1924 (Box 348, Folder 16)
    - A Primer of Economics by Elsie D. Harper, 1935 (Box 348, Folder 17)
    - Program and Administration-Tentative Work Tool, Community Division, Feb 1949 (Box 348, Folder 18)
    - Program Guide for Community Units of District and County YWCAs by Elizabeth Herring et al, 1948 (Box 348, Folder 19)
    - Program Making and Record Keeping, 1931 (Box 348, Folder 20)
    - Program Planning in the YWCA, 1956, 1959 (Box 349, Folder 1)
    - Program Planning in the YWCA, number 8 in the series on Administration in the YWCA, "The Basic Documents of a Community YWCA," 1975 (Box 349, Folder 2)
    - Program Planning Studies: A Handbook…, 1940 (Box 349, Folder 3)
    - Program Resource Organizer's Kits, 2000 (Box 349, Folder 4)
    - Program Suggestions for Members' Meetings, 1954 (Box 349, Folder 5)
    - Programs One Way or Another: A Consideration of Techniques, 1939 (Box 349, Folder 6)
    - Residences, 1939-40 (Box 349, Folder 7)
    - The Social Aspects of Our Clothes: A Study and Discussion Course in 8 Lessons by Katherine Gerwick, 1923, 1925 (Box 349, Folder 8)
    - Space Planning for a YWCA Building, Lab Division, 1932 (Box 349, Folder 9)
    - Suggested Budget Form for YWCAs in Small Cities and Towns and for Association Branches, Lab Division, 1933 (Box 349, Folder 10)
    - What's New for Women and Girls Today, reprinted from the YWCA Magazine, 1966 (Box 349, Folder 11)
    - World Fellowship Suggestions for Town Associations, 1922 (Box 349, Folder 12)
    - Series/Serials
      - House and Home Series: An Outline Course for Use with Clubs, 1919-20 (Box 349, Folder 13)
      - Program Series, 1920s (Box 349, Folder 14)
      - The Workshop Series, 1926-27 (Box 349, Folder 15)
      - Discussion Outline for Study of Work with Younger Girls, Series I, Nos. 1-6, [1930s] (Box 349, Folder 16)
      - Program Book Series, 1932-33 (Box 350, Folder 1)
      - Program Series
        - 1934-39 (Box 350, Folder 2-6)
      - Program Papers for Today and Tomorrow, 1941 (Box 350, Folder 7)
      - Program Packets
        - Nov 1944-Mar 1945, Sections 1-4 (Box 350, Folder 8-10)
        - Sections 5-10, Mar 1945- Spring 1946 (Box 351, Folder 1-8)
        - Summer 1946-Summer 1947 (Box 352, Folder 1-10)
        - Fall 1947-Winter 1950 (Box 353, Folder 1-10)
      - Memo to Staff/Program Memo to Staff/Program Memo
        - 1954-74 (Box 353, Folder 11)
        - 1964-74 (Box 354, Folder 1-3)
      - Program Priorities,1964-67: binder, 1965 (Box 354, Folder 4-6)
      - Contemporary Programming Series Kit No. 2, "Money Talk" The Wise Consumer Kit, Consumer Protection, circa 1969 (Box 354, Folder 7)
      - Contemporary Programming No. 4, Apr 1969 (Box 354, Folder 8)